Stanislaus A. Blejwas collection of the Polish American Congress Connecticut District records CPAA 86.13
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Stanislaus A. Blejwas collection of the Polish American Congress Connecticut District records.
1982-1991
CPAA 86.13
Connecticut Polish American Archives
4.0 Linear feet
This collection consists of materials collected by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas relating to the Polish American Congress Connecticut District (PAC CT) from 1981 to 1991. Stanislaus A. Blejwas was a professor of history and the director of the Polish Studies Program at Central Connecticut State University in New Britain, CT. Additionally to his professional activities he was very active in political and cultural Polish American organizations on local and national level, for which he received numerous awards and recognitions. Prof. Blejwas held several positions within the Polish American Congress, Connecticut District (PAC CT) and was a president of the organization from 1983 till 1986.
Blejwas, Stanislaus A.
Biographical/Historical note
Stanislaus A. Blejwas was born on October 5, 1941 to the Polish immigrant parents in Brooklyn, NY and raised in Clark, NJ. He graduated in 1963 Summa Cum Laude from Providence College and went on to pursue his Ph.D. in Modern East European and Polish History at Columbia University, where he graduated in 1973. He had a fellowship at the Institute on East Central Europe, an Honorary Fellowship at Columbia in 1966, and a Fulbright-Hays Fellowship to Poland a year later. Those awards were followed by a Kosciuszko Foundation Doctoral Dissertation Award in 1974, a grant from the Connecticut Humanities Council, a 1982 National Endowment for the Humanities fellowship, the Mieczyslaw Haiman Medal of the Polish American Historical Association for contributions to the field, a grant from the Kosciuszko Foundation and the Polish Ministry of Education for research at the Polish State Archives and the Polish Foreign Ministry Archives, and a distinguished service award from the Polish American Historical Association of which he was appointed president in 2001.
In June 1994, President Clinton appointed Dr. Blejwas a member of the United States Holocaust Memorial Council. He served on the Council's Research Committee and was re-appointed to a second term by President Clinton in 1999. In addition, Dr. Blejwas also acquired enormous respect abroad and was recognized in 1996 by President Aleksander Kwasniewski of the Republic of Poland who presented him with Officer of Swords of the Order of Merit of the Republic of Poland, the highest state decoration in Poland. In October of 2000, he was again honored by the Polish government with the presentation of the Foreign Minister's Diploma of Recognition for the promotion of Polish culture abroad by Professor Wladyslaw Bartoszewski, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Poland.
He was Assistant Director of Columbia University's Institute on East Central Europe before coming to Central Connecticut State University (CCSU) in New Britain, CT in 1974. After two decades as the professor of history at CCSU, Blejwas founded and held the Endowed Chair of Polish and Polish American studies. He developed the Polish Heritage Collection in CCSU's Elihu Burritt Library and organized several hundred lectures, film showings, and Polish cultural activities for the central Connecticut Polish-American community He passed away on September 23, 2001. The Polish American Congress is a national civic and political organization that has represented the interests of Polish Americans since 1944. It is considered an “umbrella organization” federation consisting of over 3,000 Polish organizations and clubs that mutually support each other. It has over one million individual members and is organized into state divisions and chapters. Main objectives of the PAC were to struggle for free and independent Poland, to provide necessary information on political situation in Poland, to encourage cooperation and support of Polish Americans for betterment of Polonia, and to combat derogatory information about Poles and Polish Americans in the media.
Scope and Contents note
The bulk of the material relates to Stanislaus A. Blejwas presidency of the PAC CT. This collection includes material before and after Dr. Blejwas' tenure as District of Connecticut President. Material consists of correspondence, photos, meeting agendas and minutes, newsletters, and newspaper articles. The dates range from 1982-1991.
Separated Materials note
Serial publications were added to Serial Publication collections located at the Connecticut Polish American Archives.
Polish American Congress; Polish American Congress -- History; Polish American Congress. Connecticut Division; Polish American Congress. Connecticut Division -- Periodicals; Polish Americans -- Connecticut
- PAC National newsletters, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- PAC state districts newsletters and activities- Eastern Massachusetts, Northern California, Wisconsin, Washington, Michigan, Pennsylvania; National bulletins and newspapers, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- PAC National- Report of the President and Executive Committee, Report of the Organizing Committee, Implementation of Helsinki Final Act, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- PAC CT- Correspondence, The Ukrainian Weekly, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- PAC CT- Meeting announcements, agendas, minutes, photos, 19883 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- PAC CT- Meeting announcements, agendas, minutes, photos, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- PAC CT- Pulaski Day Parade in Hartford- Correspondence, newspaper articles, plans, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- PAC CT- Program- Objectives and goals, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- PAC CT- Anti-defamation- Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- PAC CT- Modernization plans/ Data Fund- Proposal for computer, correspondence, donations, financial statements, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- PAC CT- Bishop Jerzy Dabrowski of Poland visit Reception- Planning documents, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- PAC CT- Solidarity International Boycott Affair – Correspondence- Ryszard Mrotek, Bronislaw Trzyzewski, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- PAC CT- Annual Picnic- Correspondence, press releases, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- PAC CT- Financial documents, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- PAC CT- Publicity- Correspondence, newspaper articles, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- PAC CT- Political Action Committee, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- PAC CT- Solidarity Fund Raising Committee- Correspondence, newspaper articles, Citation of Merit certificate, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- PAC CT- Annual Academia, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- PAC CT- Polish Affairs Committee- Correspondence, newspaper articles, handwritten notes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- PAC National Office and Board- Correspondence, bulletins, news releases, reports, meetings, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Leadership Development Conference, Washington, DC - Notes, brochures, newsletters, articles, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- PAC CT- Annual Meeting, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- PAC CT- Charitable Foundation, correspondance related to donations, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- PAC CT - Scholarship Committee- correspondence, thank you letters, applications, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- PAC CT - Mailgrams, correspondence, articles related to Radio Free Europe, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- PAC CT - Connecticut immigration matters- Court cases, correspondence, newspaper articles, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- PAC CT - Correspondence related to Connecticut Congressional Delegation, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- PAC CT - General correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- PAC CT- Monthly and quarterly meeting of officers, committee chairmen, Board of Directors & Executive Committee – minutes, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- PAC CT- Annual Meeting - financial information, various correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- PAC CT- Annual picnic- Correspondence, finances, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- PAC CT- Picnic materials given to invited politicians Nancy Johnson, Joseph Harper, Bruce Morrison, Dominik Swieszkowski, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet– Financial reports and correspondence, September, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet– Correspondence, September, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet– Committee meetings, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Publicity, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- PAC history, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Program, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Guests, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Tickets, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Photos, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Speech manuscripts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Arrangements, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Report to National Office, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary Banquet- Handouts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- PAC CT- 40th Anniversary- National Office & Board (Guest books and official program next to folder), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- National Office & Board- Close-up program, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- National Office & Board- Democratic National Committee’s Council on Ethnic Americans, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National Office & Board- Financial Statements, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- National Office & Board- Resolutions, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- National Office & Board- Charitable Foundation, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- National Office & Board- Committees and commissions, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- National Office & Board- Chicago PAC Director’s Meeting, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- National Office & Board- Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- National Office & Board- News coverage and publicity, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- National Office & Board- Polish relief, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- National Office & Board- By-laws and Amendments, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- National Office & Board- President’s and Executive Board Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- PAC- Charter Member awards, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- PAC CT- President's Report- Activities, newspaper articles, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- PAC CT- Nuclear Freeze - Speech manuscripts, articles, correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Anti- General Wojciech Jaruzelski Demonstration, New York City- Correspondence, plans, announcements, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- PAC CT- Alliance College Controversy- Correspondence, first draft of article by Andre Blaszczynski, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- PAC CT- Letter to the President Reagan, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- National Office- Resolutions, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- National Office- Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- National Office- News coverage, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- National Office- Report of President and Executive Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- National Office- Charitable Foundation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- National Office- Financial Reports, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- National Office- Committees & Commissions, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- National Office- National Directors Meeting, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- National Office- By Laws, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- National Office- Polish American Heritage Month, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- National Office & Board- Poland issues, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- PAC CT pamphlets, correspondence related to Solidarity and other Poland Issues, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- PAC CT - Connecticut Polish cultural events- lectures, banquets, anniversary celebrations, invitations, correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- PAC CT- Political activity regarding Polish affairs - Correspondence with Christopher Dodd, Nancy Johnson, and other Congress members, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- PAC CT- Finances, scholarship, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- PAC CT- Correspondence, notes, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- PAC CT- News coverage, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- PAC CT- Pulaski/Kosciuszko Parade, Hartford, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- PAC CT- Political Officials- Correspondence, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- PAC CT- Annual Meeting- Correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Myroslav Medvid affair/ United States asylum policy and procedures- Newspaper articles, correspondence, interviews, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- PAC CT- Mailing Lists, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The Statue of Liberty Ellis Island Foundation - information package, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- PAC CT- Annual Meeting- Minutes, Resolutions, Reports, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- PAC CT- Annual Meeting- Arrangements, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Miles Leland, President of the University of Bridgeport, trip to Poland controversy, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- National PAC- Correspondence, news releases, articles, (Part 1), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- National PAC- Correspondence, news releases, articles, (Part 2), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- National Council of Directors meeting- President’s report, agenda, committee reports, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- PAC CT– Political activity- Military aid to Nicaraguan Contras, Immigration Reform and Control Act of 1986, Subsidized sale of grain to Soviet Union- correspondence, notes, Congressional Records (Box 3, Folder 13)
- PAC CT– Minutes, announcements of meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Newspaper articles relating to Poland and Polish Americans, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Connecticut Democratic Committee- Jefferson-Jackson-Bailey Dinner program, by-laws amendment, correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- PAC National- Black Ribbon Day- Related correspondence, August 23, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- PAC National - PAC Brochure, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- PAC National – “Relations with Polish Regime” Brochure, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- PAC National- Polish American Heritage Month- Reports, brochures, correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- PAC National- Director's Meeting- Agenda, President's Report, correspondence- Milwaukee, June, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- PAC/Polish American Historical Association Meeting – Travel paperwork, agenda, minutes, correspondence- Milwaukee, June 11-13, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22, Folder 21)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Milwukee - Finances, agendas, reports, bulletins, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- PAC National Directors Meeting- President's Report- Elizabeth, New Jersey, November, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- PAC National Directors Meeting- Agenda, various reports, finances, handouts, correspondence- Elizabeth, New Jersey, November 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25, Folder 24)
- PAC National Directors Meeting- News release, Correspondence with President Reagan- Elizabeth, New Jersey, November, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- PAC Maryland Division - "Poles in USSR" Dispute correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago – President’s report, handouts, correspondence, news releases, charitable foundation, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago- Reports, agenda and resolutions, November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago - State Division Reports and union handouts, November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago - Report of Dukakis and Bush in Poland, November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago – Correspondence, reports, agenda, November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- PAC National Directors Meeting, Chicago - minutes, reports, November 1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- PAC National- President’s reports, budget proposal, upcoming meetings, charitable foundation, newspaper articles, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- PAC National- Correspondence, reports, curriculum for teaching WWII, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- PAC National- News releases, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- PAC CT- Correspondence, reports, news releases, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- PAC CT- Annual meeting– Handouts, agenda, February 1990 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- PAC CT- Meetings, business development tools, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- PAC CT- Tadeusz Mazowiecki reception- New York City, March 25, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- The Polish Immigrants in Adams, Massachusetts: A Case Study of the American Melting Pot by Keith E. Melder, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 41)